现在我要为我之前向你展示过的机器人添加第二个关节
Now I'm going to add a second joint to the robot that I've shown you before and this
机器人有点有趣，因为末端执行器可以达到任何特定
robot is a little bit interesting in that the end effector can reach any particular
由此描述的外部最大圆内的点，就像一个容易适应的位置
point within an outer maximum circle described by this, like an easily adaptive position
像这样，像这样的自适应位置。我的两自由度机器人可以适应
like this, like an adaptive position like that. My two-degree of freedom robot can adapt
最大圆圈内的任何xy坐标。
any x-y coordinate within the maximum circle.
有了这个两自由度机器人，虽然我们可以调整其内部的任何xy坐标
With this two-degree of freedom robot, although we can adapt any x-y coordinate within its
工作空间，它不能适应任意方向。所以，如果机器人想要在
working space, it can’t adapt an arbitrary orientation. So if the robot wants to be at
这个特殊的xy坐标，机器人的这个链接没有其他方向
this particular xy coordinate, there is no other orientation of this link of the robot
这是可能的，因为方向和位置是高度耦合的。
that's possible because orientation and position are highly coupled.
让我们按照类似的程序来确定这两个链接的末端效应器的姿势
Let's follow a similar procedure to determine the pose of the end effector of these two-link
机器人。我要记录机器人，并指出它的两个链接的长度，并指出
robot. I'm going to notate the robot and indicate the length of its two links and indicate the
两个关节角度。接下来，我们将以良好的Q1旋转出良好的坐标系。
two joint angles. Next, we're going to rotate out well coordinate frame by an amount Q1.
因此，世界参考框架现在成为此处显示的灰色坐标框架。接下来我
So a world reference frame now becomes this grey coordinate frame shown here. Next I'm
要将该坐标框架与机器人的第一个链接一起翻译，现在就是这样
going to translate that coordinate frame along with the first link of the robot so now it's
这里。我们现在已经在x方向上应用距离A1的变换。现在我
here. We've applied now a transformation in the x direction by the distance A1. Now I'm
要将帧旋转数量Q2，坐标框现在看起来像这样。
going to rotate the frame by the amount Q2, the coordinate frame now looks like this.
最后，我将在x方向上将其转换为A2。这给了我们
Finally, I'm going to translate it in the x direction by the amount A2. This gives us
连接到机器人末端执行器的坐标系，末端执行器姿势。
the coordinate frame attached to the end effector of the robot, the end effector pose.
现在我可以扩展这个表达式并将这些矩阵和结果中的每一个相乘
Now I can expand out this expression and multiply together each of these matrices and the result
这是。再一次，我们可以看一下这个齐次变换矩阵的平移路径。
is this. Once again, we can look at the translational path of this homogeneous transformation matrix.
这些元素在这里拔出，现在我有一个x和y坐标的表达式
These elements here pulling out, and now I have an expression for the x and y coordinate
我的双连杆机器人的末端执行器。再一次，我们可以看到旋转
of the end effector of my two-link robot. Once again we can see that the rotational
该变换矩阵的路径也表示末端执行器的方向
path of this transformation matrix which indicates the orientation of the end effector is also
Q1和Q2的功能。实际上它是Q1+Q2的功能。所以我们可以再次使用
a function of Q1 and Q2. In fact it’s a function of Q1+Q2. So once again, we can use
Q1和Q2独立控制x和y但我们无法独立控制方向
Q1 and Q2 to independently control x and y but we can't independently control the orientation
最后的效应器。如果我们使用Q1和Q2来选择x和y，那么方向就是
of the end effector. If we use Q1 and Q2 to choose x and y, then the orientation of the
末端效应器已经确定，可以独立选择。
end-effector is already determined and can be independently chosen.
双连杆机械手的一个有趣之处在于有两种关节角度配置
An interesting thing with a two-link manipulator is that there are two joint angle configurations
这将使末端执行器处于所需位置。这是一个配置
that will put the end effector at a desired position. Here is one configuration of the
机器人，这里是机器人的另一种配置，导致相同的结束
robot, and here is an alternative configuration of the robot that results in the same end
效应器位置。
effector position.
对于双链机器人，我已经创建了一些基于工作的变量来表示
For the two-link robot, I've already created some works based variables to represent the
链接长度，即变量A1和A2，并代表两个关节角度Q1
link lengths, that's the variables A1 and A2 and to represent the two joint angles Q1
和Q2。你可以在这里看到他们的数值。确定末端效应器姿势
and Q2. And you can see their numeric values over here. To determine the end effector pose
我需要将一些基本的同质变换链接在一起，所以我要去
I need to chain together a number of elementary homogeneous transformations so I am going
通过Q1进行旋转，然后进行平移，使x方向旋转A1，然后进行旋转
to have a rotation by Q1 followed by translation and the x direction by A1 followed by a rotation
Q2的长度，然后是链接2的长度在x方向上的平移。
of Q2, followed by a translation in the x direction by the length of link 2.
而且我将通过两个关节角度，Q1和Q2。这里我们有一个同质的转变
And I'm going to pass in the two joint angles, Q1 and Q2. Here we have a homogeneous transformation
表示双连杆机器人末端执行器的姿势和位置
representing the pose of the end effector of a two-link robot and the position of the
末端效应器由这两个数字给出，这里的2X2矩阵表示
end effector is given by these two numbers here and this 2X2 matrix here represents the
末端执行器的方向。
orientation of the end effector.
现在我们可以用符号代替这些数值，所以我定义了符号Q1和Q2
Now we can substitute these numeric values by symbols so I defined symbol Q1 and Q2 and
A1和A2的符号。我们现在可以在工作区中看到这些东西是符号对象
symbols for A1 and A2. We can see in the workspace now these things are symbolic objects as far
就MATLAB而言。我可以重复这个trchain2函数，我现在拥有的是一个
as MATLAB is concerned. And I can repeat this trchain2 function and what I have now is a
这种双连杆机器人机械手姿势的象征性表示。
symbolic representation of the pose of this two-link robot manipulator.
我可以导入一个双链接机械手的模型作为函数mdl_planar2的工具箱，和
I can import a model of a two-link manipulator as the tool box of function mdl_planar2, and
在工作中创建一个名为P2的新对象，它代表了这个机器人操纵器。
creates a new object in the works based called P2 which represents this robot manipulator.
我能做的是我可以再次调用教学方法，在这里我们看到一个双连杆机器人操纵器
What I can do is I can invoke the teach method again and here we see a two-link robot manipulator
我可以调整它的关节角度，看看它是如何移动的。在这里，我们有x和y
and I can adjust its joint angles and see how it moves. Up here we have the x and y
机器人末端执行器的坐标，我们看到在我调整关节角度时更新。
coordinates of the robot end effector and we see that that updates as I adjust the joint angles.
双连杆机械手的一个有趣的事情是有两组关节角度
An interesting thing with the two-link manipulator is that there are two sets of joint angles
这导致相同的末端执行器位置。我将使用情节方法，我要去
which result in the same end effector position. I'm going to use the plot method and I'm going
将机器人移动到一个配置，其中关节一个角度为零并且关节
to move the robot to a configuration where joint one has got an angle of zero and joint
2在两个弧度上具有pi角。
2 has an angle of pi on two radians.
在这里，我们看到了特定配置中的机器人。现在我要把它画进去
And here we see a robot in that particular configuration. Now I'm going to plot it in
一个不同的配置，这个角度将是两个pi，这个角度将是
a different configuration, that angle is going to be pi on two and this angle is going to
在两个上减去pi。
be minus pi on two.
我们看到的是机器人末端执行器具有完全相同的位置。机器人有
What we see is that the robot end effector has got exactly the same position. Robot has
在不同的配置中，末端执行器具有不同的方向但位置
a different configuration, the end effector has got a different orientation but the position
是完全一样的。
is exactly the same.